DC 1.
>> [music]
>> June the 6th, 1944.
As the Allied landings began, the 2nd SS
Panzer Division Das Reich, switched to
the Western Front from operations in the
Soviet Union, received the order to move
to the Normandy Front.
Elimar Schneider, 17, was part of a
large Alsatian contingent [music]
recently integrated by the Das Reich.
15,000 strong, and with more than 200
tanks, the division, which came under
constant attack from the resistance,
journeyed up through France, leaving a
trail of violence, summary executions,
and massacres of the civilian
population.
While the staff of the Das Reich, in the
person of General Heinz Lammerding, had
decreed the death by hanging of 99
people in Tulle, Violette Szabo, a
London-based SOE agent, parachuted a few
days earlier into the south of France to
coordinate resistance actions, was
captured by the Das Reich at
Salon-la-Tour.
Not far away, the disappearance of Major
Kämpfer, abducted by Georges Guingouin's
communist FTP, angered the commander of
the first Der Führer battalion, Adolf
Diekmann.
The village of Oradour-sur-Glane was
chosen arbitrarily as a target for
reprisals.
The battalion followed methods used
against civilian populations in Belarus,
where, in less than 4 years occupation,
628 [music] villages were razed and
their inhabitants exterminated by
formations of the SS.
June the 10th, 1944, as in Belarus, the
Das Reich shot the men in the barns of
Oradour-sur-Glane, while the women and
children were burned alive in the
church.
>> [music]
>> On the General Staff map dated June the
11th, the Germans drew a ring around the
area where the butchery was committed
the day before and in red ink noted the
figure of 500 dead.
In actual fact, 642 people were murdered
in Oradour-sur-Glane
on June the 10th, 1944.
Of the men locked in barns and sheds,
there were only five survivors.
Of the women and children burned alive
in the church, only Marguerite
Rouffanche survived.
For Diekmann, this was also about
completing the training of the rookies
under his orders.
These young Alsatians, Ukrainians, and
Hungarians had only just joined the Das
Reich.
Before the massacre, they hadn't been
blooded, as extermination [music]
strategists in the East called it.
None of them now could claim [music] to
be innocent of the crimes of the SS.
Oradour wasn't an isolated case in
Western Europe. In Italy, in Belgium, in
Greece, SS divisions sent to the West
after operating in the Soviet Union
perpetrated similar slayings
using methods employed daily in Ukraine
and Belarus.
In Italy, August the 12th, 1944, the
battalion of the 16th Panzer Division
led by Walter Reder, veteran of the
Totenkopf Division and the Battle of
Kharkov, executed the 560 women,
children, and old men of the Tuscan
village of Sant'Anna di Stazzema before
setting it alight.
Several weeks later, near Bologna, this
same unit executed the 955 inhabitants
of Mas d'Azil.
As in Oradour, no link was established
between the civilian population and any
group of partisans.
When leaving Oradour-sur-Glane,
Diekmann asked his men to say nothing of
the events of the day.
If necessary, they would say they had
[music] discovered an arms cache
belonging to the resistance to justify
the repression.
As for Helmut Kämpfe, whose
disappearance triggered the massacre, he
was executed on the direct orders of
Georges Guingouin after the head of the
communist [music] FTP heard of the SS
crimes in Oradour.
His body was never found.
The next day, a contingent of the Das
Reich returned to Oradour to erase all
traces of the massacre.
The sheds were cleared, the charred
bodies of women and children buried in a
mass grave.
Kahn and Bart's men were already back in
the main unit.
The order had [music] been given to
waste no time in reaching the Normandy
front.
>> June the 12th,
8:45 a.m.
The Das Reich Regiment was en route
north to [music] the cities of Tours and
Poitiers.
Not without difficulty, rounding up a
division spread [music] over a 30 km
radius had been no easy task.
What's more, its equipment and combat
vehicles were in an alarming state.
60% of tanks and 30% of half-tracks were
unserviceable.
The defective Panzers should have been
ditched between Montauban and Tulle.
Lammerding complained to his superiors.
Despite these annoyances, the Das Reich
still held a few trump cards. In
particular, the dozens of Panzers that
left Montauban on flatbed cars heading
for Normandy.
The SOE was aware of this.
Based on information delivered by Andre
Malraux, the Allied commander in the
region of Dordogne,
bombers were sent to pound them in the
cities of Angouleme and Poitiers.
Philippe Livry, head of Violette Szabo's
commando unit, asked the Gaullist secret
army to step up sabotage operations.
The electricity supply to the German
submarine space in Rochefort was cut.
The Paris to Limoges railway line was
dynamited.
In Salon-la-Tour, the same place that
days earlier Violette had tangled with
the Das Reich, Lievre and Mulubier
derailed two trains launched one against
the other.
It took the Germans two months [music]
to repair the rails.
By June the 13th, 91% of the 1,055
operations against the railway
programmed [music] by Allied command had
been carried out.
As for Violette Szabo, she was in deep
trouble.
Captured by the Das Reich, she'd been
handed over to the Gestapo in Limoges.
Her true identity had quickly been
[music] discovered. And the task of
interrogating her had fallen to the
executioner of Tulle, Aurel Kovac.
Her SOE comrades couldn't bring
themselves [music] to abandon her. A
rescue operation was planned for June
the 16th.
Twice a day, Violette was taken out of
her cell and walked between two
policemen to Gestapo headquarters.
They had to take advantage of those 200
m during which she was not handcuffed.
Mulubier was to fire at the two
policemen from the backseat of a car
before taking Violette.
The day came, but SOE commandos drew a
blank.
That same morning, Violette had been
transferred to Gestapo headquarters in
Paris.
By June the 18th, the Das Reich division
was only kilometers from the Normandy
front.
With its regiments gathered in Saint-Lô,
it readied itself for battle.
The Allies still only occupied a thin
strip of land along the coast.
Though the Americans gained ground
heading towards Cherbourg, the Germans
defended better than expected and held
General Montgomery's British troops in
check at Caen.
While equipment was being unloaded on
the landing beaches by the Allies,
Charles de Gaulle, just back on French
soil, was given an ovation in the
liberated town of Bayeux.
>> [cheering]
>> But nothing was yet decided.
Taking advantage of a storm to cut the
Allies' supply lines, the Germans took
back the advantage.
This was the decisive moment for the Das
Reich, which had only lost 40 men on its
slow climb towards the north.
Hellmut Schneider, the Alsatian from the
Deutschland Regiment, had a heavy heart
as the fighting drew near.
>> On the way, a huge aircraft flew [music]
over us.
At the same time, we heard explosions.
It didn't bode well, and my heart began
to beat faster.
I thought it must be an American bomber
getting rid of its last bombs that it
couldn't drop over Germany.
>> Hitler, who by now was directing
operations personally, decided to
attempt a breakthrough between Comont
and Saint-Lô.
On June the 29th, four Panzer SS
divisions were mobilized to take back
Bayeux with the Das Reich in the
vanguard.
Lammerding sent in the first battalion
of the Der Führer Regiment, that of
Diekmann and Kahn, two of the main
culprits of the massacre in
Oradour-sur-Glane.
German propaganda emphasized the
decisive nature [music] of the battle
and the fighting spirit of the troops on
the ground.
>> [music]
>> In reality, the operation was a dismal
failure. It ended in carnage for the
Germans.
After two days fighting, the Der Führer
Regiment had lost 600 men.
Diekmann was dead, decapitated by a
Sherman tank.
Kahn had his left arm ripped off. He was
repatriated to be treated at the rear.
Next day, the Das Reich positions were
pounded by 250 bombers from the Royal
Air Force.
During the month of July, the Wehrmacht
fell back, but held firm.
The Das Reich units, in support of the
German army, constantly shifted around
to contain the Allied offensives, were
at the end of their tether.
Sometimes the enemy was British,
sometimes American.
Successes were short-lived, and the
balance of power was shifting daily in
the Allies' favor.
The Das Reich had joined battle too
late.
But for the resistance ambushes and the
abuses [music] committed on the way, it
could have made the difference.
It had to make do with plugging the
holes.
Operation Cobra commenced on July the
24th.
>> [screaming]
>> No fewer than 4,000 tons of bombs rained
down on Normandy in what was the largest
display of carpet bombing in the Second
World War.
Das Reich commander, General Heinz
Lammerding, wounded during the bombing,
was evacuated from the front.
The Americans, maintaining their
positions, gained ground everywhere.
In 4 days, Coutances, Avranches, and
then Granville were liberated.
At the rear, in the region of Saint-Lô,
a welcoming committee awaited Kahn, who
was recovering from his wounds.
A military SS judge had come to hear his
version of events in Oradour-sur-Glane.
The Apostolic Nuncio and the prefect of
the Limoges region, who visited the
scene of the massacre, had complained to
[music] Pierre Laval's government of
collaborationists.
>> I want to emphasize that the village of
Oradour was one of the quietest towns in
the region, and its hard-working,
peaceful population was known for its
moderation.
These details enable you to renew your
protest to the government of the Reich,
insisting on the appallingly heinous
nature of such reprisals, the huge
emotion they have aroused, and the
terror in which [music] the people now
find themselves.
>> The Vichy government demanded
explanations.
>> The Marshall was greatly moved to learn
about the cruel and inhuman treatment
meted out to the town of
Oradour-sur-Glane
and its population.
Having made a solemn protest to the head
of the German government about such acts
that nothing can justify, he proposes to
send, as soon as circumstances permit, a
member of his cabinet to bow in his name
at the scene where so many innocent
victims and even children met with the
most appalling death.
>> The members of the resistance who
entered Oradour on June the 12th filmed
the village in ruins.
The discovery of charred corpses and
ruined buildings was an unprecedented
shock.
They sent a damning report to London
based on the testimonies of the
survivors and evidence provided by
forensic examiners.
In his statement, Kahn stuck to the line
dreamed up by Diekmann.
Oradour was hiding stocks of weapons for
the resistance.
The SS judge who delivered his verdict 6
months later aligned with this version
of events. Internally, the case was
dismissed.
French protests were not passed on to
Hitler.
The Führer's special envoy refused to
disturb him for something so trivial.
Hitler had other fish to fry.
Outraged by what he saw as his generals'
defeatism and the military setbacks on
the Normandy front, Hitler decided that
the counterattack would take place at
Mortain.
It would be led by the 2nd Panzer Das
Reich Division.
Its mission, beyond all reality, was to
throw the allies back INTO THE SEA.
>> [screaming]
>> KRIEGER!
MOMENTUM.
>> THE MORTAIN COUNTER-OFFENSIVE, quickly
halted by the Royal Air Force, was
another fiasco.
Heinz Barth was evacuated from the front
to have his wounded leg amputated.
The Das Reich
>> [music]
>> was decimated.
From over 200 operational panzers, it
was reduced to 15.
Hellmuth Schneider was caught up in the
turmoil.
>> Wherever the going was tough, our
company was involved. Mortain, Domfront,
Argentan, Falaise.
All these names remind me of episodes,
but I can't place them exactly.
With hunger gnawing away at us, we
climbed the apple trees, but the apples
were always too green and weren't good
for you.
In fact, everything here was too green.
The soldiers too young, the officers too
young. Even the weapons we couldn't try
out before for lack of ammunition. There
were so many dead and wounded that one
more or less made no difference.
Unless we're talking about comrades.
>> Even in the heart of the battle, the
Waffen SS divisions [music] continued to
hunt down partisans and notch up war
crimes.
On August the 13th, 1944, 18 people were
eliminated in Tourouvre-au-Perche
and part of the town burnt.
American prisoners of war were summarily
executed by the Das Reich on the pretext
[music] that they looked Jewish.
A German defeat was no longer in doubt.
The 100,000 soldiers in the field, the
remains of around 30 divisions in
tatters, were overwhelmed by the Allied
battering.
On August 14th, the Wehrmacht Chiefs of
Staff gave the order for a general
withdrawal.
Already weakened by the loss of 28,000
prisoners of war and 12,000 deaths in
July, the Germans lost an additional
10,000 soldiers in the Falaise pocket.
50,000 were taken prisoner.
>> [music]
[music]
>> The Das Reich was but a shadow of the
elite division it once was.
Those who miraculously survived the
Battle of Falaise slipped through Allied
fingers at the last minute.
They crossed the Seine at Elbeuf before
crossing the Ardennes.
They then disappeared the other side of
the Siegfried Line while the Allies were
making for Paris.
On August the 15th, the Allied landings
in Provence on the French Mediterranean
coast opened a new front to the west and
accelerated the disintegration of the
German forces, putting an end to any
remaining hopes of recovery.
In Paris, the staff prepared to
withdraw.
The Gestapo's most valuable prisoners,
>> [music]
>> resistance leaders and SOE agents, were
evacuated.
Exhausted by the harsh interrogation,
Violette Szabo had lost none of her
determination.
While incarcerated, she had met up with
two SOE comrades, Denise Bloch, 28, a
first-class secret agent whose Jewish
family had been rounded up by the
Gestapo in 1942,
and Lilian Rolfe, 30, half Russian, half
British radio operator arrested during a
French police crackdown.
Violette spared no effort to come to
their aid and comfort them.
The nightmare was coming to an end, she
promised them.
In reality, it had only just begun.
On August the 8th, the three women were
taken to the Gaillardet station where a
cattle train awaited them, destination
Ravensbruck.
Located some 90 km from Berlin, this
concentration [music] camp for women was
overcrowded.
Thousands of female forced workers were
piling up there.
Resistance fighters of every nationality
as well as race internees both Jewish
and Gypsy.
They served as an easily exploitable
workforce for German industries in the
region.
Violette Szabo, Denise Bloch, and Lilian
Rolfe were sent to the munitions [music]
factory in Torgau.
Working conditions were apocalyptic.
For the three resistance women, all that
mattered was surviving the camp.
They never imagined that Belarus had
been liberated by the Red Army, which
was now marching on Berlin.
While Paris had been liberated on August
the 25th, the outline of the Great Reich
was shrinking with each new Allied
victory.
But the war was not yet over.
In September, US paratroopers failed to
break through the front in the
Netherlands.
The following month, it was the
Canadians who struggled to free up
access to the port of Antwerp and fought
a difficult battle at Escaut.
Germany was bending but not yielding.
Hitler decided to attack the
Anglo-Americans in the Ardennes where
they were billeted.
The mountain range is close to the
Siegfried Line, the equivalent of the
Maginot Line, which runs along the
border with the Netherlands, Belgium,
and France.
Reputedly impassable, it had just been
reinforced on the orders of the Führer.
The German attack would be a chance to
pierce the Allied front and retake
Antwerp.
This was the last chance saloon.
It wasn't about winning the war anymore.
It was about signing a separate peace on
the Western Front.
Back in Germany, where it [music] had
taken refuge, the Das Reich was licking
its wounds.
Alsatian Ellmar Schneider, like the rest
of the division, was recovering from the
harsh fighting of the summer.
>> I celebrated my 18th birthday in
Alsace-Lorraine.
It was the first time we had some
relative peace.
The ranks of our battalion were swelling
visibly. Young Hungarians and Germans
joined us.
>> The news came in December.
Hitler had given the order to take back
the Ardennes from the Allies.
>> [music]
>> Heinz Lammerding, who had recovered
after being wounded in Normandy, was
keen to get back on the horse. The Das
Reich was renewing its offensive.
>> With the Rundstedt Offensive triggered,
it was action stations once again.
After tasting the joys of life,
we were scared again.
Very scared of dying.
>> On December the [music] 23rd, while the
fighting raged around Bastogne and St.
Vith, the Das Reich division [music]
made a sensational entry onto the
battlefield.
It fought without moderation to keep the
Americans at bay.
>> [music]
>> But once the front was set, the SS made
no headway. Doubt set in.
Alsatian Ali Marschner sank like the
rest into the American quagmire.
>> At night, while the corporal and I were
sleeping the sleep of the just,
our company received the order to take
back a hill from the Americans.
Another third of the company was out of
action,
and the Americans were still there.
>> Once the surprise had worn off, and the
dire weather that prevented
reinforcements [music] being dropped and
support bombing had dissipated, the
allies restarted air attacks and threw
all their forces into the battle.
In 3 days, German hopes were destroyed.
On December the 26th, the Das Reich was
defeated in St. Vith.
Bastogne was liberated by General
Patton.
In the months following the Ardennes
defeat, the men of the Das Reich were no
more than cannon fodder.
Dismantled into three groups to face the
Soviet advance in Czechoslovakia,
Hungary, and Dresden, the SS division
was wiped out by the Soviets in the last
exchanges of spring 1945.
Like so many others, Aurel Kovacs, who
had picked out the hanged men in Tulle,
was killed in the fighting.
Those who escaped death and the Red Army
fell back to Prague to surrender to the
Americans.
The whole of Germany was a heap of
ruins.
After Hitler's suicide in his bunker,
Lammerding, whose last mission had been
to defend Berlin, managed to slip
through the mesh of the Allied net.
Germany capitulated on May the 8th,
1945.
Violette Szabo would not taste the
victory to which she devoted her young
life.
Along with her SOE comrades Denise Bloch
and Lilianne Rolfe, she was executed
behind the Ravensbrück crematorium in
February 1945.
Two months before the liberation of the
camp by the Red Army.
Three months before the German
surrender.
Of 130,000 women deported to
Ravensbruck, only 40,000 survived the
forced labor and the medical experiments
carried out in the camp.
Violette's daughter, Tania, awaiting her
return in London, wasn't 3 years old.
She would later receive the most
prestigious decorations [music]
awarded to her mother by the British and
French authorities.
>> [music]
>> The war was over, but the crimes of the
Das Reich lived on in memory.
From 1946, the Tulle hangings and the
massacre at Oradour-sur-Glane were
mentioned in post-war courtrooms.
At the Nuremberg trials, the prosecution
tried in vain to find out who had given
the order for the massacres.
None of the Das Reich officers was
present. The question remained
unanswered.
Until the beginning of the next decade.
In January 1953, [music] after 7 years
investigation, the Oradour-sur-Glane
trial opened in Bordeaux.
A law passed in [music] September 1948
enabled the collective responsibility of
the accused to be tried.
It had been passed in [music] order to
sentence the SS for its crimes. For it
had been established at the Nuremberg
trials that it was a criminal
organization.
Robert Ebras and Marguerite Rouffanche,
two of the six survivors, came to
present [music] their testimony.
The military court in Bordeaux had to
investigate the responsibilities of 21
accused, including 14 [music]
Alsatians who claimed they were
innocent.
They were press-ganged [music]
into the SS, they protested. They were
known as the Malgré-nous, which means
against our will.
The verdict, delivered on the night of
February the 12th, triggered a wave of
protests.
There was only one death sentence
[music]
and some hard labor.
The victims' families [music] deplored
the leniency of the judgment. Those of
the Alsatians sentenced to hard labor or
prison cried [music] injustice.
They were all amnestied the following
year on the altar of national
reconciliation.
Outraged, the families of the Oradour
martyrs engraved [music] the names of
the 319 members of parliament who voted
to pass the amnesty [music] law on the
sign at the entrance to the ruined
village.
Up until 1968, they would not allow any
representatives of the French Republic
to attend [music] commemorations.
The protests also concerned those
[music] hanged in Tulle.
The victims' families pushed for the
extradition of Heinz Lammerding, the Das
Reich general who had issued the order
for the hangings.
Sentenced to death [music] in absentia
at the trial in Tulle in 1949, the
former Waffen-SS officer was living a
quiet life in West Germany, as this
December 1965 [music]
report shows.
>> [music]
[singing]
[music]
[music and singing]
[singing]
>> Despite several extradition requests,
all rejected by the German federal
authorities, Lammerding was never
bothered.
He died aged 66 in Bavaria on January
the 13th, 1971.
His comrades in the SS and the Das Reich
paid him a glowing tribute at his
funeral.
Seven years later, Otto Kahn, one of
those responsible for the
Oradour-sur-Glane massacre, died in his
turn near Munich without ever having to
answer charges for his acts.
He was 69.
Heinz Barth, his subordinate, although
sentenced to death in absentia [music]
in Bordeaux in 1953, made a career in an
industrial cooperative.
But his past did catch up with him and
he was finally tried in 1983 by a West
German court.
Robert Ebras, the Oradour survivor who
had come to testify in Bordeaux, made
the journey.
Heinz Barth's trial was also followed in
France.
The media and the TV news gave it
prominent coverage.
Sentenced to life imprisonment for his
part in the Lidice and Oradour
massacres, Barth was released in 1997.
He died 10 years later in Granze, town
of his birth, after a quiet retirement
at the age of 87.
Of the 15,000 men who took to the road
with the Das Reich, only a handful had
to answer for its crimes.
Death sentences and life sentences were
all amnestied or commuted to less severe
penalties.
The reasons cited were rebuilding,
national reconciliation,
and the Cold War.
Of the Alsatian volunteers and the
against our wills that made up the
lion's share of the troops in 1944,
none served the slightest prison
sentence.
The Alsatian Elmer Schneider was one of
them. Convince he had saved a man from
hanging, Schneider wasn't charged at the
Tulle trial. And because he wasn't
present in Oradour during the massacre,
his case was never tried.
Yet doubts persisted about his
enlistment in the SS.
In 1982,
he expressed no regrets.
>> [music]
>> Mhm.